So, huge apologies, especially to Rachel, who wasn't at the class. I forgot to record
Rachel. That shows how much I need you, that you're the one who reminds me. Huge apologies
about that. So, what I'm planning to do is just go through what we did. I hope it's all
okay and makes some sense along with the PDF. So, we talked through what we revised the strategy,
the steps that we did before for introducing Dottie Crutchett quaver, that the repertoire
is kind of crucial to everything we do. And when we're choosing that repertoire, it should have
only the known elements, the known rhythmic elements, plus the one new element, not two
new elements, only one. Then kinesthetically prepare the feeling for this concept here
in a game with at least one of the songs. Then we asked children slightly different questions.
Is there a new rhythm? Because it spans over two, there's a slightly different thing
going on here. And then we compared it with the ostinato. So, for example, we kept the
ostinato pattern going. It was ta-ti-ti-ta-ti-ti. And we used the song Nima Naya. Apologies,
the ostinato is ti-ti-ti-ti-ta-ta. And the children had to keep that ostinato going while
singing the song. Nima Naya. And discover where it matched, where what they sang matched,
or the other way to word the question, how long did the first pitch last? Nima.
And they can work out that it was three Ts, which is equivalent to three Ts tied. And then
we talked them through the dot, that two Ts tied is a ta, and the dot takes place of the third
Ti. Then we visually represented it. So, what we did in Breakout Rooms was look at similar steps
for Timka, using the song Molere Tanzen. And similarly, we kept an ostinato that was ti-ti-ka
with the kan-du. We could, of course, use an ostinato that's ti-ka-ti-ka, kan-du, to achieve
the same effect. But creating the ostinato is the important thing. So we did that in Breakout Rooms.
And then we spent the rest of the lesson looking at further repertoire for Compound Time,
for the practice of Compound Time. This is one of the final song, I think,
that we needed to analyse. So we analysed this one in class with the following tone set here.
Diatonic, literally, basically diatonic without the use of la. So start learning all of those
as we go, because we decided, I think, that the repertoire materials test would be after Christmas,
just to let us all get Christmas out of the way. And then we watched a little Maori stick passing
game. And of course, the song prepares this new rhythm here. But we talked about the fact that
this isn't really a new rhythm at all. They know ti-ka-ti-ka. It's something they know,
but in a different context. And I think when we get to A, this age, and B, this stage,
we don't need to go through every new rhythm in such detail. This is rhythms they know,
just grouped differently. The Compound Time is the new thing. So we watched this little
video here. I'm just going to play it in case you can't find it. I'll just play it for the recording.
We have been here sharing our culture with the world since 1963, when our buildings
and carvings were handcrafted in New Zealand and shipped over here piece by piece. And it
is our pleasure now to share with you a small part of our culture.
Down together four, down together five, down together six, down together seven, stop.
Thank you for playing the Tititoria. Hope to see you again soon.
Fabulous stuff. And we all agreed that it could be carnage in a classroom,
or depending on the children, it's actually possible. We discussed the sticks that you
could actually make them. I've got some here that I made just out of doweling and put a little
pattern on the top and varnished them so that there was a catching area. Softwood. Actually,
a couple of classes I've worked with really love these games. Not nearly as complex as we did
there. And shiny, glossy magazines, roll them up, sellotape them. That's another cheaper option.
Then we went on to talk about things we could do with this little chart. Here's our new rhythm
here. And we very quickly moved to this chart here to devise different things, different games.
All of these ideally would be prepared in different songs and repertoire, ideally. But again,
it's not a new rhythm, it's just a new context. So from a simplest form, moving all of these,
obviously, one beat long, just literally clapping what we saw. That was one thing we did.
And then the other thing we did was clapping two at a time, what could they memorise to.
And then we divided into two groups. One clapped round this way, and the other clapped round this
way. And then we tried something really challenging. One group clapped this way,
or sorry, everybody clapping this way, saying the rhythm names. Sorry, not clapping. Everybody
saying the rhythm names this way to hear, but at the same time clapping the pattern they see on the
other side. We did that very slowly. It was fine here, but when we get to here, it's a bit more
challenging. So again, just differentiated learning activities for the children. Singing a song
and clapping a different ostinato pattern created from here, or singing a song they know and just
clapping, not an ostinato, but literally wherever the leader points. So advanced practice activities,
these were all advanced. We looked at clapping this rhythm, top part rhythm, which was really
a rhythm, and then the second half just beat. Similarly on the bottom beat, then just rhythm.
Could the children put those two things together? One part with one hand and one part with the
other hand. That led then to composition activity, creating over the beat, remembering what groups
as a beat. So compound time takes a lot of practice. So this composition obviously would be
a much later activity. Then we looked at this activity here and what the challenges might be
singing this in two parts. Not too difficult to sing from a pitch perspective because it really
moves largely by step. Things that might catch them out just when it doesn't move by step here
at the end. But how would we prepare it? And we talked about the possibility of practicing
any difficult intervals, although there aren't so many in here, or circling things that might
catch them out. But largely maybe singing the top melody, clapping the bottom so that they
could do this as a kind of singing clap exercise. And moving on from that, singing in two parts.
I did say the quotation that Kodai used, it's not an exact word for word, but something like
if the sight singing of children is too difficult that they're wading through it and it's challenging,
then there's no point in the sight singing. That they should feel rhythmically how it goes,
it should be rhythmically fluent. And obviously when children sight sing, there's going to be
some errors, but they should largely be rhythmically fluent with what they do. So,
preparing it or giving children sight singing that's maybe slightly lower than their level of
reading ability. Their singing ability is here, but their reading ability is always a bit lower.
Speedbody boat, this is why we did team cat again. Team cat isn't a new rhythm,
they've done the rhythm, it's just a different grouping of that rhythm.
And then we worked a tiny bit on harmony, a compound time melody. We did this as a creative
text exercise. So, where it was the Isle of Skye on an apple pie, we changed it. The leader sings
maybe to the Isle of Mull. And the children have to come up with honour. And I can't remember what
we came up with, because I can't remember if I used Isle and Mull, but it could be on a skeleton
skull and back again by morning. So, we did a bit of creative text around that. And then we looked at
this holding the Do as a pedal all the way through, and then explaining what that triad would be.
And if this is chord one based on Do, could the children work out what would be chord five,
which is the fifth note, and build the triad there. Then we put the new triad into context
in the scale. As a Do, so Do, little accompaniment. Then we added chord four for this
beat here. Similarly, the children can work this out. And then we have another baseline part. Or,
we could create different parts from the whole triad. This is a very simple baseline using the
root of the triad. But of course, the kids could do something much more interesting.
Much more interesting. Going from tonic to dominant. Whatever the chord pattern would be,
they choose their pathway through. So, there's our song with the accompaniment.
Then it became a composition activity. Writing their own accompaniment. There's the rhythm is
given, but the children have to choose from the triad. So, they could choose literally just the
root note, but it would be much more interesting if they chose a pathway through. Much more
interesting as a class activity. Then we looked at framing some sight singing. So, framing by
singing the first beat of the bar, rather than showing them everything at once, which can be
just a bit overwhelming. Gradually taking bits away. Bit more each time. Obviously, we sang all
this through in the class. And then revealing the whole thing. But by the time we've got to here,
they've sung the framework. So, they've got a fair idea of how it goes.
And the last thing we did was look at creating a game for 9-8 and 12-8.
Now, we went into breakout rooms. How would we feel 9-8 and 12-8 through a game? Sorry,
just 9-8. Apologies, not 12-8. How would we feel 9-8? We should feel the beat, but we should also
feel the subdivision. So, that was a very quick summary of what we did in our lesson. It would
have been much more interesting to see all of your faces and have that recording. Unfortunately,
stupid me forgot to press record. There's a bit more here on the PDF. We'll quickly go over that
just in the next class, because it's really just how we introduced the children to the idea of
simple and compound time. That will be on the PDF forever, however. So, sorry again for forgetting
to record. I hope the summary is in some way helpful, and I'll see you on Friday. All the best. Bye!